{"tossups": [{"question": "A controversial 2005 book by Claude Ribbe argued that this country\u2019s troops used sulfur dioxide to construct gas chambers in ships, killing tens of thousands of black slaves. A civil commissioner named Sonthonax ruled troops in a colony of this country that experienced a massive slave rebellion in 1791. This country\u2019s control over the western portion of Hispanola was ended by an insurrection partially led by Toussaint L\u2019Ouverture. For the point, name this country that oversaw Haiti as the colony of Saint-Domingue.", "answer": "<b> France</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This country introduced social welfare programs like Bolsa Familia and Fome Zero during the 2000s. The 2016 Copa Sudamericana was posthumously given to a team from this country after the crash of LaMia Flight 2933 en route to Colombia. Sergio Moro led Operation Car Wash in this country, which uncovered widespread corruption in this country\u2019s state-run oil company. For the point, name this country where Michel Temer became president after the impeachment of Dilma Rousseff.", "answer": "Federative Republic of<b> Brazil</b>", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "The scope of this organization was drastically and controversially reduced by one of its leaders, Anne Gorsuch. This organization determined that many children attending the 93rd and 99th Street schools had sustained chromosomal damage due to the Love Canal scandal. This organization largely manages the Superfund, and it was established by a Richard Nixon executive order in 1970. For the point, name this government organization that oversees pollution testing.", "answer": "<b> Environmental Protection Agency</b> (or<b> EPA</b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Matthew Fontaine Maury designed torpedoes that were used by this navy, which was coordinated by Stephen Mallory. The<em> Housatonic</em> was sunk by a submarine operated by this navy, the<em> Hunley</em>. Officer Raphael Semmes captained this navy\u2019s commerce raider<em> Alabama</em>, and this navy used blockade runners to smuggle cotton out of its ports. For the point, name this navy, which was blamed for the loss of New Orleans to Union forces in 1862.", "answer": "navy of the<b> Confederacy</b> (accept navy of the<b> Confederate</b> States of America; accept navy of the<b> CSA</b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "According to legend, this island\u2019s first settlement was at Anakena. This island\u2019s first European visitor was Jacob Roggeveen in 1722, and its natives developed the still-undeciphered rongorongo script. Jared Diamond argued this island\u2019s society collapsed due to deforestation. Natives here used tuff to carve figures that were all toppled from their<em> ahu</em> platforms between European contact and 1868. Chile now controls, for the point, what Pacific island whose Rapa Nui people built giant stone heads known as moai?", "answer": "<b> Easter</b> Island (accept<b> Rapa Nui</b> before mentioned)", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {}, {}, {"question": "The victor of this battle founded the city of Nicopolis in celebration. During this battle, Quintus Dellius betrayed the plans of the losing side, whose quinqueremes proved too unwieldy to deal with Liburnians. Titus Taurus\u2019 ground troops were not utilized in this battle, as much of it took place in the Ambracian Gulf. Marcus Agrippa led the fleet of one side in this battle, where defeat prompted Cleopatra and Marc Antony to commit suicide. For the point, name this 31 BC naval victory for Octavian.", "answer": "Battle of<b> Actium</b>", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "This man invented a precursor to the calculator, consisting of a cylindrical device with winding teeth of incremental length, known as his namesake \u201cwheel.\u201d This man introduced the dx and dy notation for derivatives, which overtook the dot notation developed at Cambridge. Voltaire mocked this philosopher in<em> Candide</em> for claiming that we live in the best of all possible worlds. For the point, name this German philosopher and mathematician who, at the same time as Isaac Newton, developed calculus.", "answer": "Gottfried<b> Leibniz</b>", "metadata": "Science - Other Science - Math"}, {"question": "William Alden Smith led a U.S. Senate probe into this event in an attempt to find malpractice. In 2016, Senan Molony suggested that this event was caused by a three-week-long coal fire, which weakened the bulkhead. The<em> Californian</em> failed to respond quickly to this event, which was described as an \u201cact of God\u201d when the White Star Line was found not to be at fault. Survivors of this event were rescued by the <em>Carpathia</em> from lifeboats. For the point, name this 1912 disaster involving a British passenger liner that struck an iceberg in the North Atlantic.", "answer": "sinking of the RMS<b> Titanic</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This man was killed while on an expedition to Scythia by their queen Tomyris. This man overthrew his grandfather Astyages [ah-STY-ah-geez] of the Median Empire and defeated Croesus [kree-sus] to conquer the Lydians. From his capital of Pasargadae [pass-ar-gah-dye], he created a system of satraps to govern his empire, and this ruler authorized the Jews\u2019 return to Israel after his conquest of Babylonia. For the point, name this \u201cGreat\u201d founder of the Persian Empire.", "answer": "<b> Cyrus the Great</b> (or<b> Cyrus II</b> of Persia; prompt on Cyrus alone before \u201cGreat\u201d is read; accept Cyrus alone after \u201cGreat\u201d is read)", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "One holder of this position dealt with a tax revolt led by John Pratt and James Bistor. Harold Washington was the first black holder of this position, and died in office in 1987. Another holder of this position who died while holding it noted \u201cI\u2019m glad it was me instead of you\u201d after being shot in the lung by Giuseppe Zangara. Anton Cermak and two members of the Daley family served in, for the point, what position held by Rahm Emanuel as chief executive of the largest city in Illinois?", "answer": "<b> Mayor of Chicago</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {}, {"question": "In a novel by this author, society is split into a class of engineers and managers and a class comprised of everyone else after World War III causes the complete automation of industry. The town of Ilium serves as a setting of this writer\u2019s novel about Paul Proteus. A character created by this man repeatedly becomes\u201cunstuck in time,\u201d causing him to relive the firebombing of Dresden during World War II. For the point, name this author of<em> Player Piano</em> and<em> Slaughterhouse-Five</em>.", "answer": "Kurt<b> Vonnegut</b> Jr.", "metadata": "Literature - American Literature - Misc Literature"}, {}, {"question": "Robert Guiscard ended this empire\u2019s presence in Apulia by capturing Bari. A princess of this empire married Vladimir of Rus\u2019 after his conversion to Christianity, while another described political intrigue in the<em> Alexiad</em>. This empire\u2019s split over the practice of iconoclasm was ended by its Empress Irene. This empire\u2019s defeat at Manzikert while defending Asia Minor led to the rise of Alexios I and the call for the First Crusade. For the point, name this Orthodox empire centered at Constantinople.", "answer": "<b> Byzantine</b> Empire (or<b> Eastern Roman</b> Empire)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This ally of Jos\u00b4e F\u00b4elix Ribas pondered the fate of numerous occupied countries in a letter to Henry Cullen sent from Jamaica. He argued for the death of all unsupportive<em> peninsulares</em> in his \u201cDecree of War to the Death,\u201d which was issued shortly after he took Merida in the Admirable Campaign. This president of Gran Colombia defeated the Spanish at Carabobo, securing the independence of Venezuela. For the point, name this 19th century liberator of South America.", "answer": "Simon<b> Bolivar</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "This man sold his land holdings at Willow Run to enable the construction of a bomber factory during World War Two. This man\u2019s personal secretary, Ernest Liebold, pushed him to acquire<em> The Dearborn</em> <em>Independent</em> to promulgate his anti-Semitic views. This man established the five-dollar workday and quipped that people could purchase his company\u2019s signature product in any color they liked, so long as that color was black. For the point, name this American automaker who marketed the Model T.", "answer": "Henry<b> Ford</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "A house in this city contained a mosaic, based on a Greek painting, showing Darius III fleeing from Alexander the Great at the Battle of Issus. Scenes of the cult worship of Dionysus can be viewed in this city\u2019s Villa of the Mysteries. This city\u2019s Lupanar, a brothel, famously features well-preserved graffiti. From across the Bay of Naples, Pliny the Younger wrote about a disaster in this city. For the point, name this Roman city that, like Herculaneum, was ruined by the 79 AD eruption of Mount Vesuvius.", "answer": "<b> Pompeii</b>", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "This state\u2019s westernmost region, purchased from the Chickasaw Indians by Andrew Jackson, includes an exclave known as its namesake \u201cbend.\u201d Most of the unrecognized Transylvania Colony was located in this state. A national forest here contains the Red River Gorge and is named after a frontiersman who blazed the Wilderness Road into this state, also home to the world\u2019s largest cave system. Mammoth Cave and the Daniel Boone National Forest are found in, for the point, what \u201cbluegrass\u201d state with capital Frankfort?", "answer": "<b> Kentucky</b>", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "One member of this party criticized it in the essay \u201cWild Lily.\u201d A longtime leader of this party used the slogan \u201cto rebel is justified,\u201d while a later leader established its \u201cfour cardinal principles\u201d in response to the Democracy Wall movement. A statue of the Goddess of Democracy was set up to protest this party; troops who opened fire on it were defied by Tank Man. For the point, name this political party that carried out the Tiananmen Square Massacre and which has led mainland China since 1949.", "answer": "<b> Chinese</b> <b>Communist</b> Party (or<b> CCP</b>, or<b> Zhongguo</b> <b>Gongchandang</b>; prompt on \u201cCommunist\u201d until \u201cChina\u201d is read, then accept it)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "A supply convoy headed to this city was intercepted in the Battle of the Herrings. The loss of the Tourelles complex forced one army to withdraw from this city, where the Earl of Salisbury was slain. The destruction of bridges across the Loire [LWAH] delayed the capture of this city, which was relieved by a peasant woman who had visions of the Archangel Michael instructing her to protect France. For the point, name this city that was saved by the arrival of Joan of Arc in the Hundred Years War.", "answer": "<b> Orleans</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "This event was predicted by Roger Babson, the namesake of a \u201cBreak\u201d that preceded this event by about a month. This event was investigated by a commission led by Ferdinand Pecora. In the lead-up to this event, P-E ratios peaked at an all-time high of 32.6, and this event worsened as margin calls came in. This event encompassed days called Black Thursday, Monday, and Tuesday. For the point, name this economic event that marked the end of the Roaring Twenties and triggered the Great Depression.", "answer": "Stock Market<b> Crash of 1929</b> (accept other elaborations, like Wall Street<b> Crash of 1929</b>, Dow<b> Crash of 1929</b>, etc.; prompt on stock market crash, etc., if given without the year; prompt on Black Thursday, Monday, and/or Tuesday before mentioned; prompt on Great Depression before mentioned)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "In 1851, the first international tournament of this game took place in London; during a break in the action, Adolf Anderssen and Lionel Kieseritzky competed in the \u201cImmortal Game.\u201d This game\u2019s\u201cGame of the Century,\u201d played at the Marshall Club in New York, involved former U.S. Open champion Donald Byrne losing to a 13-year-old. For the point, name this game, mastered by Bobby Fischer, Magnus Carlsen, and the Deep Blue computer, which often concludes with a checkmate.", "answer": "<b> chess</b>", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {"question": "A treaty ending this war called for the creation of the United Baltic Duchy. A major and rare success for one country in this war was the Brusilov Offensive, which targeted Galicia. That country suffered two disastrous defeats during this war at the First Battle of the Masurian Lakes and Tannenberg. One power withdrew from this war at the Treaty of Brest-Litovsk. For the point, name this war that Russia withdrew from after being taken over by the Bolsheviks, after it fought with Britain and France against Imperial Germany.", "answer": "<b> World War I</b> (accept the<b> Great</b> War)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "This man\u2019s teacher during the Second Sophistic, Herodes Atticus, was completely ignored by this author during his later works. While on deployment, James Mattis was known to carry a copy of this man\u2019s most famous work. This man constantly calls for himself to evaluate life from a cosmic perspective in a book written while on campaign against the Marcomanni tribes in Germania. For the point, name this Stoic Roman Emperor and author of the<em> Meditations</em>.", "answer": "<b> Marcus Aurelius</b> Antoninus Augustus", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}], "bonuses": []}